Guide to the Eli Cantor Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Eli Cantor Papers
1935-1985.
Cantor, Eli.
21.5 linear feet (46 document boxes).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
MS#0190
4079656
Biographical Note
American author, lawyer, & printer.
Scope and Content
Manuscripts, notes, correspondence, printed materials, and books.
Arrangement
Material is arranged into three series:
Series I: Manucripts
Series II: Printed Material
Series III: Research Institute of America
Subjects
Research Institute of America, inc.; Authors, American.; Economics.; Articles.; Contracts.; First drafts.; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts.; Memorandums.; Notes.; Novels.; Proofs.; Reports.; Scripts.; Theses.; Authors.; Economists.; Lawyers.; Novelists.; Printers.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least two business days in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
"Brass Ring" correspondence in Box 1 and "Enemy in the Mirror" correspondence in Box 9 are closed.
Acquisition
1986 M-1986 Cantor, Eli Gift
Gift of Eli Cantor, 1984 & 1986.
- Series I: Manuscripts
  The collection contains typescript manuscripts with handwritten corrections of Cantor's novels, "Enemy in the Mirror" (N.Y.: Crown Books, 1977) and "Love Letters" (N.Y.: Crown Books, 1980); printed works composed by Gallery 33 of the Composing Room, which Cantor headed from 196l to 1971; and articles by Cantor from various magazines, including "Esquire" and "Coronet". Also included are typescript manuscripts of "The Rite" (N.Y.: Zebra Books, 1979) and "The Nest" (N.Y.: Zebra Books, 1980), novels written by Cantor under the pseudonym Gregory A. Douglas.
  - "Black Market"(1942) (Box 1)
    - Typescript (carbon) (Box 1)
    - Related Material (Box 1)
  - "Blue Bird of Happiness"--Typescript (photocopy) (Box 1)
  - The Brass Ring
    - 1st Version (1980)
      - Typescript with notes, (9 folders) (Box 1)
      - Related Correspondence (Box 1)
    - 2nd Version (1981-1982)--Typescript with notes, (6 folders) (Box 2)
    - 3rd Version (1982)
      - Typescript, (8 folders) (Box 2)
      - Additional titlepage, etc. (Box 3)
    - 4th Version (1982-1983)
      - Typescript, (7 folders) (Box 3)
      - Outage, (4 folders) (Box 3)
      - Related Items (Box 3)
    - 5th Version (1983). (Box 4)
      - Typescript, (6 folders) (Box 4)
      - Typescript with notes, (6 folders) (Box 4)
      - Flap-copy (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous notes (Box 4)
    - 6th Version (1985).Typescript, (8 folders) (Box 5)
    - 7th Version (1985).Typescript, (5 folders) (Box 5)
  - Candy Store (Box 6)
    - Version I (1945). Typescript (Box 6)
    - Version II (1945) Typescript, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - 3rd version Typescript, 1948, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Working Draft (Box 6)
    - Synopsis (Box 6)
  - The Case of the Warrens (1943).--Typescript (Box 6)
  - Cookbook Project (Box 6)
  - "The Curving Road"(1945) Typescript, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Enemy in the Mirror (Box 7)
    - 1st version (1971-1972)
      - Typescript, (14 folders) (Box 7)
      - Typescript (photocopy), (7 folders) (Box 7)
      - Notes (Box 8)
      - Related Correspondence (Box 8)
      - Articles and Clippings (Box 8)
    - 2nd version (1972)
      - Typescript, (14 folders) (Box 8)
      - Outage, (6 folders) (Box 9)
    - 3rd version (1973)--typescript (carbon), (12 folders) (Box 9)
    - 4th version (1974-1975)
      - Typescript (folders 1-3) (Box 9)
      - Typescript (folders 4-9) (Box 10)
      - Typescript (photocopy), (9 folders) (Box 10)
      - Notes and Clippings (Box 10)
      - Notes and Revisions (Box 10)
    - Edited 4th version (1976)
      - Typescript with corrections (folders 1-5) (Box 10)
      - Typescript with corrections (folders 6-13) (Box 11)
    - 5th version (1976)
      - Typescript, (10 folders) (Box 11)
      - Photocopies (Box 11)
      - Photocopies (Box 12)
    - 6th version (1977)
      - Typescript (l4 folders) (Box 12)
    - Production manuscript, (1977)
      - Typescript, (7 folders) (Box 12)
      - Typescript (continued), (6 folders) (Box 13)
    - "Insurance" copy (1977)
      - Typescript (l)-(l6) (Box 13)
      - Notes and clippings (Box 13)
  - The Golden Goblet (Box 14)
    - 1st version (1961).--Typescript (Box 14)
    - New version (1962).--Typescript mimeo, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - 1st musical version (1972-1973).Typescript, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - 2nd musical version (1978).
      - Typescript, (2 folders) (Box 14)
      - Related correspondence (Box 14)
    - 3rd musical version (1978).-Typescript, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Love Letters (Box 15)
    - Author's Original (1978)
      - Typescript, (6 folders) (Box 15)
      - Notes and Clippings (Box 15)
    - 2nd version (1978). Typescript.(photocopy), (6 folders) (Box 15)
    - 3rd version (1978).Typescript (l)-(6) (Box 15)
    - 4th version (1978).Typescript (l)-(7) (Box 16)
    - 5th version (1978).Typescript (l)-(8) (Box 16)
    - Production manuscript. (1978). (Box 17)
      - Typescript, (7 folders) (Box 17)
      - Uncorrected proof (1979) (Box 17)
      - Film Contract, (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - Screenplay. 1st draft (1978)., (3 folders) (Box 17)
  - "The Methodology of Bergson and Spengler." (M.A. Philosophy thesis, N.Y.U.) (Box 17)
  - The Nest (Box 18)
    - 1st version (1979-1980)
      - Typescript (l2 folders) (Box 18)
      - Notes and revisions (Box 18)
      - Research material (Box 18)
    - 2nd version (1980)
      - Typescript, (7 folders) (Box 18)
      - t.ms.(photocopy) (l)-(7) (Box 19)
      - Photocopies (Box 19)
      - Page Proofs, (l)-(5) (Box 19)
  - The Rite (Box 20)
    - Draft (1973).
      - Clippings and Notes (Box 20)
      - Draft of first approach (Box 20)
      - First approach (July 1973) (Box 20)
      - typescript, (3 folders) (Box 20)
      - Notes (Box 20)
      - Outage, (4 folders) (Box 20)
    - Author's Original (1974)
      - Typescript, (5 folders) (Box 20)
      - Typescript, continued, (2 folders) (Box 21)
      - Typescript, (7 folders) (Box 21)
      - Typescript (carbon), (7 folders) (Box 21)
      - Notes, clippings & correspondence (Box 21)
    - 3rd version (1975).
      - Typescript, (4 folders) (Box 21)
      - Typescript, continued, (2 folders) (Box 22)
      - Outage, (3 folders) (Box 22)
    - 4th version (1975)
      - Typescript, (5 folders) (Box 22)
      - Outage, (5 folders) (Box 22)
    - Revision of 4th version (Box 22)
    - 4th-5th revisions--Notes and clippings (Box 22)
    - 5th version (1977) (Box 23)
      - Typescript, (7 folders) (Box 23)
      - Outage, (9 folders) (Box 23)
    - 6th version (1979)
      - Typescript (photocopy) (folders l-3) (Box 23)
      - Typescript, continued (photocopy) (folders 4-8) (Box 24)
      - Out-takes (Box 24)
      - Page-proofs, (4 folders) (Box 24)
      - Insert to Galleys (Box 24)
  - White Hat with Trumpets
    - Typescript (carbon) (Box 24)
    - Typescript with notes (Box 24)
  - Yes, There are Buffalo in Italy
    - Typescript (mimeo) with notes (Box 24)
    - Typescript (mimeo) (Box 24)
    - Related items (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, (2 folders) (Box 24)
- Series II: Printed Matter
  - "Adventure in the Morning." Story XIX, no. 92 (Nov-Dec (Box 25)
  - "America 1975 The Corporation." Challenge 4 no. 7 (April 1956) (Box 25)
  - "Black Artists in Graphics." Ideal 10U (Box 25)
  - "Corporations in Tomorrow's World." Management Review (June 1956) (Box 25)
  - "Day of Days," Esquire (June I9U0) (Box 25)
  - CGraphic AnnouncementsD Gallery 33 (The Composing Room) (Box 25)
  - "Holiday Greetings." Ideal 94 (Box 25)
  - "Perils of the Typographic Market in 1972." Typographical Journal l6l, no. 1 (Box 25)
  - The Research Institute (Box 25)
    (Articles in The Atlantic & the Saturday Review)
  - "Songs for the Times, i-xiii." Poetry xlix, no. 1 (1936) (Box 25)
  - "Take Me, Missus, Take Me." Accent (Winter (Box 25)
  - "You Can Make Music." Coronet (December 1939) (Box 25)
  - "You, The People." Coronet (November 1939) (Box 25)
  - The Devils Pi. Illustrated by Milton Glaser. N.Y.: The Composing Room, 1967. (Box 26)
  - Enemy in the Mirror. New York: Crown Publishers, 1977 (hardcover) (Box 26)
  - Enemy in the Mirror. New York: Zebra Books, 1977 (paperback) (Box 26)
  - Love Letters. New York: Crown Publishers, 1979. (hardcover) (Box 26)
  - Love Letters. New York: Zebra Books, 1979 (paperback) (Box 26)
  - [Gregory A. Douglas, pseud.]
    - The Nest. N.Y.: Zebra Books, 1980. (paperback) (Box 26)
    - The Rite. N.Y.: Zebra Books, 1979. (paperback) (Box 26)
  - Typefaces. New York: The Composing Room, undated (Box 26)
  - User's Guide to Phototypography. New York: The Composing Room. (Box 26)
- Series III: Research Institute of America
  This series of the collection contains 59 bound volumes of publications, edited by Cantor, from the "Research Institute of America", a New York based organization devoted to economic affairs.
  - Series III.1: Research Institute of America Files
    - Analysis (Box 27)
      - 1942-1944 (Box 27)
        (includes special analysis of the American War Economy)
      - 1945-1956 (Box 28)
      - 1957-1959 (Box 29)
    - Foreign Cables, 1945 (Box 29)
    - Research Institute Letters, 1945-1946 (Box 29)
    - Research Institute Recommendations
      - 1951-1954 (Box 30)
      - 1955-1959 (Box 31)
    - Research Institute Reports
      - 1944 (Box 31)
      - 1945-1947 (Box 32)
      - 1948-1949 (Box 33)
      - 1950-1955 (Box 34)
        (1951-1953 missing)
      - 1956-1959 (Box 35)
    - Research Institute Studies, 1954-1957 (Box 35)
    - Research Institute's Letter to Accountants, 1951-1952 (Box 35)
  - Subseries III.2: Executive Membership
    - Executive Policy Letter
      - 1944-1948 (Box 36)
      - 1949-1950 (Box 37)
      - 1951-1952 (Box 38)
      - 1953 (Box 39)
    - Policy Memoranda, 1944-1953 (Box 39)
    - Reports
      - 1944 (Box 39)
      - 1945-1946 (Box 40)
      - 1946-1949 (Box 41)
      - 1950-1951 (Box 42)
      - 1952-1953 (Box 43)
    - Staff Reports to Members
      - 1954-1955 (Box 44)
      - 1956-1957 (Box 45)
      - 1958-1960 (Box 46)